<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Posts on Personal Portfolio and Blog</title>
        <link>//localhost:1313/posts/</link>
        <description>Recent content in Posts on Personal Portfolio and Blog</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <copyright>&lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a&gt;</copyright>
        <lastBuildDate>Sat, 26 Apr 2025 10:39:39 -0400</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="//localhost:1313/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
        
        <item>
            <title>Authority</title>
            <link>//localhost:1313/posts/authority/</link>
            <pubDate>Sat, 26 Apr 2025 10:39:39 -0400</pubDate>
            
            <guid>//localhost:1313/posts/authority/</guid>
            <description></description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>The Lord&#39;s Supper</title>
            <link>//localhost:1313/posts/communion/</link>
            <pubDate>Wed, 23 Apr 2025 18:35:33 -0400</pubDate>
            
            <guid>//localhost:1313/posts/communion/</guid>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cdn11.bigcommerce.com/s-e49v9azv2t/images/stencil/1280x1280/products/292/1029/WCC-WineWafer_DoubleStack__10481.1692282654.1280.1280__92113.1719806502.jpg?c=1&#34; alt=&#34;Prepackaged Communion Elemenets&#34; title=&#34;Prepackaged Communion Elemenets&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eating and drinking are central to primitive and modern fellowship. There is one meal that we esteem most highly: the Lord&amp;rsquo;s Supper. It has become a formalized and ritualistic affair — so lacking in physical sustinence that it is more gesture than literal meal. When partaking of the Supper, members of the Church mirror Jesus&amp;rsquo; actions in Mark 14:22-26 with emblems of bread and drink while meditating on some aspect of the crucifixion.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn11.bigcommerce.com/s-e49v9azv2t/images/stencil/1280x1280/products/292/1029/WCC-WineWafer_DoubleStack__10481.1692282654.1280.1280__92113.1719806502.jpg?c=1" alt="Prepackaged Communion Elemenets" title="Prepackaged Communion Elemenets"></p>
<p>Eating and drinking are central to primitive and modern fellowship. There is one meal that we esteem most highly: the Lord&rsquo;s Supper. It has become a formalized and ritualistic affair — so lacking in physical sustinence that it is more gesture than literal meal. When partaking of the Supper, members of the Church mirror Jesus&rsquo; actions in Mark 14:22-26 with emblems of bread and drink while meditating on some aspect of the crucifixion.</p>
<ol>
<li>The bread is the Body of Christ</li>
<li>The cup (of wine or juice) is the Blood of Christ</li>
<li>A prayer of blessing is said over each before consumption</li>
</ol>
<p>There are many parallels between this &ldquo;rite&rdquo; and the old Passover. One major divergence is the lack of proper instruction defining when and how the Supper should be observed, which has resulted in wildly varied doctrines. Where some traditions hold to monthly schedules, Churches of Christ almost uniformly require weekly observance strictly on Sunday (as the Lord&rsquo;s Day). Yet there are variables even within this doctrine: should the Supper be offered more than once on Sunday? Should an evening service be held in which morning absentees get the chance to partake? Should the rest of the congregation abstain from a second round? How should the emblems be distributed? Should the bread be broken by individual participants or an officiant? Should all drink from one cup?</p>
<p>Point: the Biblically recorded accounts of the Lord&rsquo;s Supper lack sufficient specificity to be entirely prescriptive. What is prescriptive? Our Lord&rsquo;s instruction to &ldquo;do this in remembrance of&rdquo; him. Add to this Paul&rsquo;s admonishment to self examination for worthy participation in the body and blood. Almost everything else about the Lord&rsquo;s Supper is circumstantial.</p>
<table>
  <thead>
      <tr>
          <th>Issue</th>
          <th>Teaching</th>
          <th>Authority</th>
      </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
      <tr>
          <td>Frequency</td>
          <td>Offered every Sunday, exclusive</td>
          <td>Circumstance</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>Participation</td>
          <td>One observance per week, when offered</td>
          <td>Tradition</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>Occasion</td>
          <td>During formal assembly</td>
          <td>Circumstance</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>Elements</td>
          <td>Bread, fruit of the vine</td>
          <td>Example</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>Form</td>
          <td>Unleavened bread, unfermented grape juice</td>
          <td>Circumstance</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>Method</td>
          <td>Distributed elements consumed after a blessing</td>
          <td>Example</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>Purpose</td>
          <td>To remember Christ and partake in his body and blood</td>
          <td>Instruction</td>
      </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="frequency-participation-and-occasion">Frequency, Participation, and Occasion</h2>
<p>This is the least discussed aspect of the Lord&rsquo;s Supper in the Bible, but the Church of Christ doctrine in this regard is the most entrenched. Condemnation of others from Church of Christ preachers and teachers, in the context of the Lord&rsquo;s Supper, is likely to be over some discrepancy in the occasion or frequency of the offending party&rsquo;s implementation. Some congregationalist churches offer the Lord&rsquo;s Supper monthly, and many denominations offer it too often or too infrequently for Church of Christ tastes.</p>
<p>The Church of Christ is mostly uniform in offering the Lord&rsquo;s Supper every week on Sunday — and only Sunday — during corporate assembly as an act of worship. Their argument for this stems from a particular interpretational approach to scripture colloquially known as <a href="../authority">CENI</a>. This <em>hermenutic,</em> in short, states that nothing is permissible unless authorized in the Bible by command, approved Apostolic example, or necessary inference. The Lord&rsquo;s Supper, therefore, is practiced in the Churches of Christ in a manner that seems to them most consistent with the Bible record within their frame of interpretation.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Both [in I Corinthians 11] and when the Lord’s Supper was instituted, the frequency of the partaking is not mentioned. It only says as often as it is done. It is from Acts 20:7 that we learn that the disciples partook of the Lord’s Supper on the first day of the week. This then is the frequency it is to be partaken &ndash; every first day of the week. The duration is given in I Corinthians 11. This memorial is to be done until the Lord returns.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup></p></blockquote>
<p>This statement is a succinct encapsulation of the Church of Christ position, and it necessarily excludes the assumptions the author makes in order to affirm a doctrine without expressing the level of estimation involved. Acts 20:7 reads:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>On the first day of the week, when the <mark>disciples were gathered together to break bread</mark>, Paul talked with them, intending to depart on the next day; and continued his speech until midnight. <strong>— Acts 20:7, WEB</strong></p></blockquote>
<p>Note that the author of the Church of Christ statement writes &ldquo;Lord&rsquo;s Supper&rdquo; where &ldquo;break bread&rdquo; is written in Acts 20. He assumes they are interchangable in this context, and defends his assumption elsewhere:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>I Corinthians 11:22 and 34 tell us that the Lord&rsquo;s Supper was not a common meal to be eaten individually in people&rsquo;s homes. Compare this to Acts 2:42, &ldquo;And they continued steadfastly in the apostles&rsquo; doctrine and fellowship, in the breaking of bread, and in prayers.&rdquo; Here the breaking of bread is listed among items of worship: Learning God&rsquo;s word, assembling, and praying. In Acts 2:42, the phrase refers to the Lord&rsquo;s Supper.</p>
<p>Now, concerning Acts 20:7, what do we learn from the context? First, it was done on Sundays when the disciples came together for the purpose of breaking bread. Whatever the meal was, it was something that only occurred once a week. If it was a common meal, you would not expect it to be restricted to a single day of the week. After all, in Acts 2:46 we see that sharing meals was sometimes a daily event. But this particular meal made Sundays an important day of the week. Second, it required the disciples to come together to partake of this breaking of bread. This calls to mind Paul&rsquo;s discussion of the Lord&rsquo;s Supper in I Corinthians 11. Notice how often the phrase &ldquo;come together&rdquo; appears in this discussion (I Corinthians 11:17, 18, 20, 33). Third, while some early churches meet in a disciple&rsquo;s home, the group in Troas meet in an upper room (Acts 20:8). Once again, we see that this is a special gathering, separate from the home.</p>
<p>The conclusion can only be that Acts 20:7 is referring to the partaking of the Lord&rsquo;s Supper.<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup></p></blockquote>
<p>In the CENI hermenutic, this is an application of <em>necessary inference</em>. The author uses a certain logical flow to arrive at what he might call an inescapable conclusion, that is, &ldquo;that Acts 20:7 is referring to the partaking of the Lord&rsquo;s Supper.&rdquo; Invalidating a necessary inference only requires that an alternative be found, and examining the author&rsquo;s logic quickly shows there are several alternative inferences that lead to a different conclusion.</p>
<ul>
<li>Nothing makes Sunday restrictive</li>
<li>Coming together for a meal is not unique to the Lord&rsquo;s Supper</li>
<li>The location, outside of a home, does not necessitate a special occasion</li>
</ul>
<p>Since it is possible that the disciples shared a meal while gathered in a communal place on Sunday (as other disciples had done and as a straight reading of this passage conveys), <mark>there is nothing that logically necessitates interpreting Acts 20:7 to be the singular pattern for the Lord&rsquo;s Supper</mark>.</p>
<p>Of course, gathering on Sunday to partake of the Lord&rsquo;s Supper is perfectly valid as it does not violate or disregard any information we actually do have concerning its observance.</p>
<h2 id="elements-and-form">Elements and Form</h2>
<h2 id="method">Method</h2>
<h2 id="purpose">Purpose</h2>
<h1 id="notes">Notes</h1>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>“Lord’s Supper.” Articles. La Vista Church of Christ, January 30, 2021. <a href="https://www.lavistachurchofchrist.org/cms/lords-supper/">https://www.lavistachurchofchrist.org/cms/lords-supper/</a>.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>&ldquo;Does Acts 20:7 refer to a common meal?&rdquo; Answers. December 1, 2003. <a href="https://www.lavistachurchofchrist.org/cms/does-acts-207-refer-to-a-common-meal/">https://www.lavistachurchofchrist.org/cms/does-acts-207-refer-to-a-common-meal/</a>&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Eldership</title>
            <link>//localhost:1313/posts/eldership/</link>
            <pubDate>Sun, 06 Apr 2025 18:35:33 -0400</pubDate>
            
            <guid>//localhost:1313/posts/eldership/</guid>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;My church is beginning the process of searching out men to serve as new elders alongside the eldership we&amp;rsquo;ve had for the past 11 years. This congregation has not had to consider this issue to my knowledge for at least that long, so the sermon today started a series of studies that will refresh us on why we need an eldership and who we should look for to fill that role.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My church is beginning the process of searching out men to serve as new elders alongside the eldership we&rsquo;ve had for the past 11 years. This congregation has not had to consider this issue to my knowledge for at least that long, so the sermon today started a series of studies that will refresh us on why we need an eldership and who we should look for to fill that role.</p>
<p>I attended one church regularly in the past that did not have elders; they were goverened by a &ldquo;men&rsquo;s meeting&rdquo; that was more or less democratic. This isn&rsquo;t a biblical concept, but it&rsquo;s usually justified by the necessity to have <em>some</em> leadership when a congregation lacks willing, able, and/or qualified men to take the elder&rsquo;s office. That church never attempted to appoint elders while I was there, and, actually, I think I&rsquo;ve managed not to be present when any of my childhood congregations went through the process. (Maybe once, but not that I can confidently say was the appointment of a new elder.)</p>
<p>There was, however, a time when I really resented the structure and perception of elders in the Church of Christ and I definitely came to the idea that we had the whole concept wrong. There was plently of emotional motivation behind that whole study though, so I won&rsquo;t rely on it now. Instead, what I&rsquo;m going to do is record my <strong>impressions/off-the-cuff thoughts</strong> about eldership in the next section — without any initial study aside from today&rsquo;s sermon — so that I may have a better chance of identifying biases when I study and fill out the subsequent sections of this post. Hope that makes sense.</p>
<h2 id="impressions">Impressions</h2>
<p>Everything we know about an early-church eldership is from Paul and it&rsquo;s mostly indirect. He doesn&rsquo;t give much instruction directly to elders or tell them how to do their job or even what their job is in real detail. Where elders are required is ambiguous as well; does &ldquo;every city&rdquo; then translate to &ldquo;every church&rdquo; today? I know the argument for a plurality of elders is based on the reading that elders are always mentioned in the plural and never singularly in the context of a church office, but the lack of postive affirmation on this point can&rsquo;t be ignored. Elders are always spiritual leaders in the Bible, never <em>executive</em> or <em>business</em> leaders. The only possible exception I can think of to this is the implied distribution of aid to Judea&hellip; but then it&rsquo;s not clear whose elders received the collection.</p>
<p>Today&rsquo;s elders seem mostly executive. They run the church, manage a staff of deacons, make financial decisions, and deal with the personal problems of members throughout the congregation. They also set the tone for doctrine and teaching in the church. They hire the preacher, are usually listed on the church&rsquo;s charter or articles of incorporation, and generally take on accountability for the church&rsquo;s property and resources. They serve more as directors of an institution than spiritual shepherds.</p>
<p>The executiveness or directorly appearance of the modern eldership is, to me, largely due to the institutional nature of today&rsquo;s congregations. They are often incorporated, own property and do business as a legal entity. Naturally there arises a structure of people to run the entity — deacons as treasurers, grounds keepers, programers, and ministry leaders, elders as the final decision makers and approval stampers. I&rsquo;m not trying to downplay the very heavy burden of the church&rsquo;s people themselves, either. Elders are also counselors and comforters, they visit members in need, bring those needs to the attentions of the congregation, and sometimes divert resources to relieve them. Let&rsquo;s not forget that they serve as gatekeepers of a sort too, and choose when it&rsquo;s appropriate to remove members from the church.</p>
<p>(I&rsquo;m not going to clean this section up all that much, if it&rsquo;s wrong it&rsquo;s wrong&hellip; hopefully this post will conclude with a better informed view after much study and prayer.)</p>
<h2 id="the-study-begins">The study begins</h2>
<p>A good place to start is with a prayer.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Father God, please guide me in this study and help me to put past feelings behind so that they won&rsquo;t twist my understanding now. Give me wisdom and a godly understanding of the eldership so that I may not hinder this church in the pursuit of good leadership. In Jesus&rsquo; name I pray, amen.</p></blockquote>
<p>The basic passages I&rsquo;ll read:</p>
<pre><code>- 1 Peter 5:1-5
- Acts 20:17-38
- 1 Tim 3:1-7
- Titus 1:5-9
- Hebrews 13:7, 17
- Ephesians 4:11
- Acts 14:21-23
- Acts 11:30
</code></pre>
<h3 id="pauls-farewell-to-the-ephesian-elders">Paul&rsquo;s Farewell to the Ephesian Elders</h3>
<blockquote>
<p><sup><strong>17</strong></sup> From Miletus he sent to Ephesus and called to himself the elders of the assembly. <sup><strong>18</strong></sup> When they had come to him, he said to them, “You yourselves know, from the first day that I set foot in Asia, how I was with you all the time, <sup><strong>19</strong></sup> serving the Lord with all humility, with many tears, and with trials which happened to me by the plots of the Jews; <sup><strong>20</strong></sup> how I didn’t shrink from declaring to you anything that was profitable, teaching you publicly and from house to house, <sup><strong>21</strong></sup> testifying both to Jews and to Greeks repentance toward God and faith toward our Lord Jesus. <sup><strong>22</strong></sup> Now, behold, I go bound by the Spirit to Jerusalem, not knowing what will happen to me there; <sup><strong>23</strong></sup> except that the Holy Spirit testifies in every city, saying that bonds and afflictions wait for me. <sup><strong>24</strong></sup> But these things don’t count; nor do I hold my life dear to myself, so that I may finish my race with joy, and the ministry which I received from the Lord Jesus, to fully testify to the Good News of the grace of God.</p>
<p><sup><strong>25</strong></sup> “Now, behold, I know that you all, among whom I went about preaching God’s Kingdom, will see my face no more. <sup><strong>26</strong></sup> Therefore I testify to you today that I am clean from the blood of all men, <sup><strong>27</strong></sup> for I didn’t shrink from declaring to you the whole counsel of God. <sup><strong>28</strong></sup> Take heed, therefore, to yourselves and to all the flock, in which the Holy Spirit has made you overseers, to shepherd the assembly of the Lord and God which he purchased with his own blood. <sup><strong>29</strong></sup> For I know that after my departure, vicious wolves will enter in among you, not sparing the flock. <sup><strong>30</strong></sup> Men will arise from among your own selves, speaking perverse things, to draw away the disciples after them. <sup><strong>31</strong></sup> Therefore watch, remembering that for a period of three years I didn’t cease to admonish everyone night and day with tears. <sup><strong>32</strong></sup> Now, brothers, I entrust you to God and to the word of his grace, which is able to build up and to give you the inheritance among all those who are sanctified. <sup><strong>33</strong></sup> I coveted no one’s silver, gold, or clothing. <sup><strong>34</strong></sup> You yourselves know that these hands served my necessities, and those who were with me. <sup><strong>35</strong></sup> In all things I gave you an example, that so laboring you ought to help the weak, and to remember the words of the Lord Jesus, that he himself said, ‘It is more blessed to give than to receive.’ ”</p>
<p><sup><strong>36</strong></sup> When he had spoken these things, he knelt down and prayed with them all. <sup><strong>37</strong></sup> They all wept freely, and fell on Paul’s neck and kissed him, <sup><strong>38</strong></sup> sorrowing most of all because of the word which he had spoken, that they should see his face no more. Then they accompanied him to the ship. <strong>— Acts 20:17-38</strong></p></blockquote>
<h4 id="takeaway">Takeaway</h4>
<p>Aside from the scene, Paul gives the elders a couple of lines of instruction: <em>&ldquo;Pay attention to and shepherd your flock from the wolves that will come, even from among you, drawing disciples away. Watch &ndash; my example is unceasing &ndash; don&rsquo;t let your guard down and don&rsquo;t give up.</em> Concerning the role of elders, this passage boils down to earnest defense of the word of God and correct understanding of it within the group they have purview over.</p>
<h3 id="peters-exhortation">Peter&rsquo;s Exhortation</h3>
<blockquote>
<p><sup><strong>1</strong></sup> Therefore I exhort the elders among you, as a fellow elder and a witness of the sufferings of Christ, and who will also share in the glory that will be revealed: <sup><strong>2</strong></sup> shepherd the flock of God which is among you, exercising the oversight, not under compulsion, but voluntarily; not for dishonest gain, but willingly; <sup><strong>3</strong></sup> not as lording it over those entrusted to you, but making yourselves examples to the flock. <sup><strong>4</strong></sup> When the chief Shepherd is revealed, you will receive the crown of glory that doesn’t fade away.</p>
<p><sup><strong>5</strong></sup> Likewise, you younger ones, be subject to the elder. Yes, all of you clothe yourselves with humility and subject yourselves to one another; for “God resists the proud, but gives grace to the humble.” <strong>– 1 Peter 5:1-5</strong></p></blockquote>
<h4 id="takeaway-1">Takeaway</h4>
<p>Adding to Paul&rsquo;s instruction that elders should be vigilant defenders, Peter clarifies that elders must not &ldquo;lord it over&rdquo; (or, as I read it, &ldquo;boss around&rdquo;) their flock. They don&rsquo;t tell us what to do, but they do show us the way and drive out those who are a detriment to good faith.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>My faith</title>
            <link>//localhost:1313/posts/workbench/</link>
            <pubDate>Sat, 05 Apr 2025 16:51:20 -0400</pubDate>
            
            <guid>//localhost:1313/posts/workbench/</guid>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m a Christian, and I want to follow Jesus. I was raised in the church but left, did many sinful things along the way, and within the past couple of years have found my way back out of a sense of guilt. Now I&amp;rsquo;m trying to stay for better reasons — primarily that I love God for what he offers and want to be a productive member of his kingdom.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m a Christian, and I want to follow Jesus. I was raised in the church but left, did many sinful things along the way, and within the past couple of years have found my way back out of a sense of guilt. Now I&rsquo;m trying to stay for better reasons — primarily that I love God for what he offers and want to be a productive member of his kingdom.</p>
<h1 id="what-im-starting-with">What I&rsquo;m starting with</h1>
<blockquote>
<p>God created and set our universe in motion; he maintains our physical existance and provides spiritual redemption by his son, Jesus — God made man.</p></blockquote>
<p>I guess that&rsquo;s the best I can do at writing a one-line statement of faith. Growing up in the Church of Christ (acappella, non-institutional branch if you&rsquo;re wondering) gave me a very stark perspective of right and wrong: either you&rsquo;re completely cleansed, or you&rsquo;ve committed one unconfessed sin and are lost. Somehow I still ended up justifying many lawless things I did (or suppressing my conscience to enable them), so as a disciplinary tool damnation wasn&rsquo;t effective at keeping me out of trouble, but it did come back to haunt me in later years. Grown up and out of the CoC, I deconstructed enough to leave all but the fear of the Lord behind.</p>
<p>Eventually, something that sparked a feeling of guilt brought the fear to the forefront of my mind. It took over and I suffered through a year and more both righting past wrongs and trying to be &ldquo;righteous&rdquo;. Guilt-motivation brought me to real depression — I lost weight, my heart never seemed to stop racing while I was awake, I couldn&rsquo;t easily have fun or enjoy entertainment, etc. I realize, intellectually, that a lot of my anxiety was unnecessary because it was more about getting worldly things right than it was about relying on God&rsquo;s promised grace and forgiveness.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>God is faithful to forgive. Forgetting about the past, I focus on what is to come.</p></blockquote>
<p>Much better to be anxious to please God in what I am doing now than trying to wipe the slate clean myself. That&rsquo;s something only God can do anyway, and there&rsquo;s nothing works-related that I can do to add to my salvation. So, now, a little older and a bit worse for wear, I want to return to regular Biblical studies and share some of what I find to be good and vent now and then about what gets on my nerves.</p>
<h1 id="what-i-think-about-the-hard-questions">What I think about the hard questions</h1>
<p>These are just my thoughts: some are more well informed than others and I&rsquo;ve been wrong enough times to know I can be wrong now too. <em>I&rsquo;m also a bit rusty (the hiatus I mentioned above).</em></p>
<h2 id="freewill-or-predestination">Freewill or Predestination?</h2>
<p>I think I&rsquo;ve come around to my mom&rsquo;s take on this one. In so many words: &ldquo;I think it is true that God will accomplish his will within the framework of human freewill. &hellip; None of us have the choice not to be accountable to God, but we all have the choice whether to serve him willingly with our lives, bowing the knee out of true devotion and faithfulness, or to serve him like Pharaoh did, and be forced to our knee against our will in the end. God hardens people’s hearts by repeatedly confronting them with the truth they do not want.&rdquo;</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
